總頁數: 10
--- 第 1 頁 ---
Liu et al. BMC Ophthalmology (2023) 23:1
https://doi.org/10.1186/s12886-022-02764-6
RESEARCH Open Access
Association between whole-grain
intake and myopia in chinese children:
a cross-sectional epidemiological study
Zhuzhu Liu1, Qingxin Wang1, Qianyu Zhao2, Fei Gao1, Nan Jin1, Di Wang1, Biying Wang1, Bei Du1* and
Ruihua Wei1*
Abstract
Background: Nutritional status influences the growth and development of the eyes. However, there are few studies
on the association between diet, especially whole grains (WG) consumption, and myopia. The study aimed to evalu-
ate the association between WG intake and myopia prevalence among primary school-age children in China.
Methods: This cross-sectional epidemiological study conducted between November 2019 and December 2019
included 586 children, aged 6–12 years, attending primary school in Binhai district, Tianjin, China. Ophthalmologic
examinations and optometric cycloplegic refraction measurements were conducted. Information was collected on
known risks and protective factors for myopia and the consumption of WGs, vegetables, and fruits. This association
between the probability of myopia and the proportion of WG consumption (WG proportion was calculated as the
mean intake from WG sources divided by total grain intake), adjusted for protective and risk factors, was analysed
using crude and multivariable logistic regression.
Results: Among the study participants, 226/586 (38.57%) children had myopia in at least one eye. WG intake was
inversely correlated with the prevalence of myopia. Furthermore, in the multivariate analysis, WG intake of > 50% was
identified as a protective factor against myopia after subsequent adjustment for children’s age, sex, parental myopia,
near-work activity, screen time, reading and writing habits, visual fatigue, outdoor time, and classroom light environ-
ment (all P < 0.05).
Conclusion: WG intake (> 50%) was an independent protective factor against myopia. Modifying the form of grains
consumed (whole versus refined) could be one of the targets of future public health measures.
Keywords: Myopia, Protective factors, Diet, Whole grains, Near work
Background 60% of the world’s population) will exhibit myopia world-
Myopia is a significant public health problem worldwide wide by 2050 [1]. Myopia is an irreversible eye disease,
and the largest attributable risk factor for vision loss. It often accompanied by complications, such as retinal
has been predicted that 4.8 billion people (approximately detachment, macular disease, macular haemorrhage,
choroidal neovascularisation, and glaucoma, when it pro-
gresses to high myopia [2]. Therefore, it is necessary to
*Correspondence: dubei1982@126.com; rwei@tmu.edu.cn investigate the factors influencing this rapidly growing
1 Tianjin Key Laboratory of Retinal Functions and Diseases, Tianjin Branch prevalence.
of National Clinical Research Center for Ocular Disease, Eye Institute, School With the rapid time-scale increase in myopia (less than
of Optometry, Tianjin Medical University Eye Hospital, Tianjin, China
2 to 3 generations), several non-genetic associated factors
Full list of author information is available at the end of the article
© The Author(s) 2023. Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which
permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the
original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or
other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line
to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory
regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this
licence, visit http:// creat iveco mmons. org/ licen ses/ by/4. 0/. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http:// creat ivec o
mmons. org/ publi cdoma in/ zero/1. 0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.
--- 第 2 頁 ---
Liu et al. BMC Ophthalmology (2023) 23:1 Page 2 of 10
have been identified. Time spent doing near-work, screen children aged between 6 and 12 years. The exclusion
time duration, and less time outdoors are the most fre- criteria were (1) a history of systemic or ocular disease
quently cited environmental factors underlying the that required treatment, including keratitis, ocular aller-
development of myopia [3–6]. During the developmen- gic disease, any other ocular surface disease, glaucoma,
tal ages at which myopia develops in children, diet, as a active or chronic uveitis, or previous ocular surgery
non-genetic associated factor, is primarily set by family or injury, and (2) a history of using atropine eyedrops,
characteristics, including wealth and culture. Economic orthokeratology, or any method to prevent or control
development is often accompanied by diet changes, myopia.
as reflected in the secular increases in height reported The study protocol was approved by the Institutional
in many countries worldwide. Axial length growth is Ethics Committee of Tianjin Medical University Eye
driven by physical development at an early age, whereas Hospital (approval no. 2019KY-12) and followed the ten-
its excessive growth is dominated by myopia develop- ets of the Declaration of Helsinki for research involving
ment [7]; thus, it is plausible that deficits in nutritional humans. The parents or legal guardians provided written
intake and status could play a role in its development informed consent on behalf of all participants.
and progression. To date, the association between diet
and myopia has not been extensively studied, especially
Eye examination and measurement
in Chinese children. Over 200 years since the Industrial
All children underwent comprehensive eye examina-
Revolution, a change has occurred from low to high-gly-
tions, including measurements of distance visual acuity
caemic load carbohydrates, as increasingly higher levels
and intraocular pressure, non-cycloplegic and cyclople-
of refined sugars have been incorporated into the diet
gic refraction, slit lamp microscopy, and digital fundus
along with more refined grains [8]. In 2002, Cordain et al.
photography. The international standard visual chart was
[9] proposed that consumption of refined carbohydrates
used to evaluate uncorrected and corrected visual acuity.
(starches and sugars) could be involved in the develop-
A slit lamp, tonometer, and ophthalmoscope were used
ment of juvenile-onset myopia via hyperinsulinism;
for ocular health examination. In addition, cycloplegia
increased insulin may affect the hormonal regulation of
was achieved by instilling three drops of 1% cyclopento-
eye growth and increase axial elongation. This hypothesis
late 5 min apart in each eye. Subsequently, 30 min after
has been supported by more recent evidence [10–15].
the last drop, another drop of 1% cyclopentolate was
Grain products, especially those made from whole grains
administered if the pupil size was < 6 mm or if the pupil-
(WGs), have received particular interest because they
lary light reflex was still present. Autorefraction was per-
can influence the digestion rate and decrease the blood
formed 35 min after the last drop.
glucose response. Studies on WGs intake have reported a
Refraction was measured in patients with ciliary
reduced risk of type II diabetes with higher consumption
paralysis using an Auto Refractometer (KR-800, Top-
of WGs [16, 17]. Moreover, WGs constitute a significant
con, Tokyo, Japan), and three successive measurements
source of beneficial nutrients, such as dietary fibre, phy-
were recorded and averaged. All three readings had to
tochemicals, minerals, several vitamins, and other sup-
be 0.25 D apart in both the spherical and cylindrical
plements [18, 19]. All these ingredients are abundant in ≤
components. The spherical equivalent refraction was cal-
WGs but are lacking in refined grains, which are a major
culated as the spherical refractive error 1/2 of the cylin-
source of high-glycaemic carbohydrates. +
drical refractive error, and participants with a spherical
Currently, the long-term effect of WG versus refined
equivalent refraction 0.50 D in either eye were classi-
grain consumption on the prevalence of myopia has ≤−
fied as having myopia.
not been extensively studied, especially in Chinese chil-
dren whose lifestyle and diet patterns have changed dra-
matically. This study aimed to evaluate the association Dietary intake assessment
between WGs and the prevalence of myopia to provide
Food consumption data were collected through a dietary
comprehensive evidence to improve prevention, treat-
history interview, including the habitual diet over the
ment, and management of myopia.
past year. The interviewers were nutritionists who used
a questionnaire listing 122 foods, with the usual serving
Methods
sizes of WGs, refined grains, vegetables, and fruit items
Study design and population in common household measures (e.g., soup spoons, rice
A multi-stage stratified cluster sampling method was bowls, and cups). The children’s parents or guardians
adopted, and three classes were randomly selected in were asked to recall the usual intake of each food item
each grade (1–6). Ultimately, 634 students in 20 classes on the list for the past year as an indicator of the partici-
were included in this study. The inclusion criterion was pants’ long-term diet. Food images were provided, and
--- 第 3 頁 ---
L iu et al. BMC Ophthalmology (2023) 23:1 Page 3 of 10
food models were used to help participants remember and high myopia); near-work activity (including distance
the portion sizes of specific foods. and hours per week); screen time (hours per week using
WG variables were classified using a modified version electronic devices and watching television); reading and
of Jacobs et al.‘s procedure [20]. Individual WG foods writing habits (including reading posture, the distance
(serving/day), including WG flour and other products between fingertip and nib, and head angle); frequency of
(Coix seed, brown rice, sorghum, black rice, barley, yel- visual fatigue per week; outdoor times; and light environ-
low rice, corn, oats, highland barley, buckwheat, wheat, ment in the classroom. These factors were included as
millet, and amaranth grain), with a WG or bran con- covariates in different multivariable logistic regression
tent 25% by dry weight, were calculated by multiply- models, as these elements have been demonstrated to
≥
ing the pre-specified serving size by the reported intake have possible associations with myopia in previous stud-
frequency of each food. Fruit intake was calculated by ies [5, 22–25].
summing the servings of strawberries, prunes, bananas,
blueberries, grapefruit, cantaloupe, raisins, apples, blue- Statistical analysis
berries, pears, peaches, watermelon, and oranges. Veg- Descriptive results for the participant characteristics are
etable intake was estimated by summing the servings of described using means (standard errors) for continuous
alfalfa sprouts, cabbage, coleslaw, cauliflower, Brussels variables and frequencies (percentages) for categori-
sprouts, carrots, corn, peas, mixed vegetables, beans, cal variables. Participant characteristics were compared
broccoli, lentils, yams, spinach, squash, kale, lettuce, between the non-myopia and myopia groups using Wil-
beets, celery, tomatoes, and potatoes. Fruit and vegetable coxon rank sum tests, Z statistic for continuous variables,
juices were not included in the assessment of fruit and and the χ2 test for categorical variables. To estimate the
vegetable intake. The ingredients of the mixed foods were relationship between WG and the health outcome of
broken down into their component foods and assessed myopia, univariate and multivariate logistic regression
using a recipe file. Finally, the reported portion of each models were constructed to determine the relationship
serving was converted to gram weight, and the intake of between WGs and the prevalence of myopia. Usual WG
different food items was combined. intake was treated as an explanatory variable for myopia
in univariate and multivariate logistic regression, with
Population categorisation < 25% as the reference category.
The proportion of WG consumption was calculated Model 1 was adjusted for age, sex, and school type
as the mean intake from WG sources divided by total (public versus private), while Model 2 was additionally
grain intake. The parents or guardians self-reported adjusted for parental myopia. In Model 3, covariates,
the proportion of WG in all grains, fruit intake (g/day), including near-work activity, screen time, reading and
and vegetable intake (g/day). Furthermore, participants writing habits, and times of visual fatigue per week, were
were categorised into three WG intake groups based on further added to the model, Model 4 was additionally
the proportion of WG in all grains consumed per day: adjusted for time spent outdoors per week and light envi-
low WG (< 25%), medium (25–50%), and high (> 50%). ronment in the classroom (whether classroom curtains
This categorisation was chosen following the dietary are often open). Model 5 was further adjusted for intake
guidelines of the United States, which recommend that of fruits and vegetables. The effect modification of asso-
consumers eat at least half their grains as WGs [21]. ciations between WG and myopia incidence was tested
Moreover, the study population was divided into ter- by stratified analyses of age (6–8 years vs. 9–12 years)
tiles based on total dietary vegetable and fruit intake (g/ and sex (female vs. male). P-interaction values were cal-
day): vegetable (< 75 g/day, 75–150 g/day, > 150 g /day) culated using the likelihood ratio test to include a cross-
and fruit (< 75 g/day, 75–150 g/day, > 150 g/day). All product term of the ordinal categorical exposure and a
tests were performed with the proportion of WG in all 2-category effect modifier. All probabilities quoted were
grains as the exposure measure, and one-day recall data two-sided, and all statistical analyses were performed
were estimated using a predictor of true nutrient intake, using the Statistical Package for Social Sciences version
including fruits and vegetables as covariates, to aid 13.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). A P value 0.05 was
≤
estimation. considered significant.
Covariate measurements Results
Participants completed questionnaires to provide infor- A total of 586 students (273 girls and 313 boys) com-
mation on various known or suspected risks and pro- pleted the examinations and questionnaire survey
tective factors for myopia as follows: age; sex; parental between November 2019 and December 2019, and
myopia (including the number of parents with myopia the response rate was 92.43% (586/634). Of the 586
--- 第 4 頁 ---
Liu et al. BMC Ophthalmology (2023) 23:1 Page 4 of 10
participants, a significant proportion (38.57%) had myo- between the intake of WG and myopia. When stratified
pia, and the average equivalent spherical power of 1172 by sex, a stronger association with WGs was observed
eyes was 0.11 D 1.63 D. The characteristics of the among female students than male students. For boys,
− ±
patients with and without myopia are shown in Table 1. WG intake of 25–50% (P 0.485) was not a protective
=
Significant differences were observed regarding age, factor; only an intake > 50% of WGs was identified as a
sex, parental myopia, near-work activity (distance and protective factor against myopia (OR 0.209, P 0.047).
= =
hours per week), reading posture, times of visual fatigue In girls, when adjusting for covariates, WG consump-
per week, the light environment in the classroom, and tion > 50% still significantly influenced the prevalence of
outdoor time between participants with and without myopia (OR 0.214, P 0.041). Furthermore, WG intake
= =
myopia (P < 0.05). Different multivariable logistic regres- was non-significant in children aged 6–8 years, whereas
sion models and variance inflation factors (AIC) were WG intake > 50% remained protective against myopia for
checked to avoid over-correcting. The VIF of all variables children aged 9–12 years.
were below 10, indicating no multicollinearity problems.
In multivariate logistic analysis, compared with having Discussion
parents without myopia, having more parents with myo-
This study aimed to evaluate conjoint modifiable risk fac-
pia (one parent with myopia, odds ratio [OR] 2.061,
= tors involved in myopia prevalence in a Chinese children
P 0.024; two parents with myopia, OR 4.541,
= = population, including the impact of WG consumption. In
P < 0.001) was positively associated with myopia, but
this cross-sectional study, we found a significant associa-
male sex (OR 0.544, P 0.006), elevated light levels
= = tion between increased WG intake and reduced myopia
in the classroom (classroom curtains are often open,
prevalence, especially among children aged 9–12 years,
OR 0.544, P 0.048), and higher proportions of WGs
= = after adjusting for several demographic and lifestyle fac-
(> 50%, OR 0.370, P 0.036) were negatively associated
= = tors. Some risk/protective factors of myopia were con-
with myopia (Fig. 1).
currently detected: parental myopia was significantly
The association between WG intake and myopia in
associated with an increased probability of myopia, but
crude and multivariable logistic regression models is
male sex and elevated light environment in the classroom
presented in Table 2. In the crude model, we used the
seemed protective.
presence of myopia as a dependent parameter and a WG
Many studies have confirmed that a family history
percentage 25% as the reference. A 25–50% WG intake
≤ of myopia is a risk factor for developing myopia [26,
was not a significant factor in the prevalence of myopia
27], which was similarly observed in the present study.
(OR 0.855, P 0.405), but intake > 50% (OR 0.48;
= = = Multivariable logistic regression analysis showed that
P 0.017) was a protective factor against myopia. Mul-
= compared to children without a myopic parent, chil-
tivariable-adjusted ORs (95% confidence intervals) for
dren with one myopic parent (OR 2.061, P 0.024)
= =
myopia are shown in Models 1–5. In Model 1, using age,
and both myopic parents (OR 4.541, P < 0.001) were
=
sex, and type of school (public versus private) as covari-
at a higher risk to prevalence of myopia. Josh Wall-
ates, we found that the prevalence of myopia remained
man pointed out that the effect could possibly as well
significantly associated with WG consumption > 50% but
be explained if myopic parents, who are more likely to
not with WG intake of 25–50% (P 0.446). In Model 2
= be wealthier and better educated, create more myopi-
(parental myopia was additionally entered into the logis-
genic environments [28]. Recently, Guggenheim has
tic regression model), > 50% WG intake remained signifi-
also suggested that genetic effects explain only part of
cant. Further adjustments for near-work activity, screen
the impact of parental myopia [29]. Currently, hun-
time, reading and writing habits, and times of visual
dreds of genetic loci have been identified for refrac-
fatigue per week in Model 3 and light environment in
tive error and myopia, and risk variants mostly carry
Model 4 (outdoor times per week and light levels in the
low risk but are highly prevalent in the general popu-
classroom) did not significantly alter the association.
lation. Most researchers have now accepted the argu-
Additional adjustments for dietary factors in Model 5
ment that genetics cannot have a major role, except in
(intake of fruits and vegetables) did not substantially alter
the rare cases that are predominantly genetic, because
the association. Conversely, fruit and vegetable intake
the rate at which gene pools change is inconsistent with
was not significantly associated with myopia’s prevalence
the speed at which the epidemic of myopia has emerged
in the simple or multivariable logistic regression models
[30, 31]. Like many other traits, common myopia is
(P > 0.05).
complex in its pathogenesis and progression, with con-
Results from the analyses stratified by sex and age are
tributions from genetic and environmental factors,
shown in Table 3. No interactions were observed for
including lifestyle, reduced outdoor time, and inten-
age (P 0.846) and sex (P 0.978) in the relationship
= = sive near-work activities [5, 22–25]. A combination of
--- 第 5 頁 ---
L iu et al. BMC Ophthalmology (2023) 23:1 Page 5 of 10
Table 1 Characteristics of all participants
Characteristics All participants Subgroup participants P value
(586)
Non-myopia (360) Myopia (226)
Age P < 0.001**
6–8 years 333 268 (80.48%) 65 (19.52%)
9–12 years 253 92 (36.36%) 161 (63.64%)
Sex P 0.001**
=
Female 273 148 (54.21%) 125 (45.79%)
Male 313 212 (67.73%) 101 (32.27%)
Duration of electronic device use per week P 0.078
=
0–7 h 328 213 (64.94%) 115 (35.06%)
7–14 h 184 110 (59.78%) 74 (40.22%)
14–21 h 50 27 (54.00%) 23 (46.00%)
>21 h 24 10 (41.67%) 14 (58.33%)
Duration of watching television per week P 0.594
=
0–7 h 416 250 (60.10%) 166 (39.90%)
7–14 h 126 84 (66.67%) 42 (33.33%)
14–21 h 30 18 (60.00%) 12 (40.00%)
>21 h 14 8 (57.14%) 6 (42.86%)
Duration of near work per week P < 0.001**
0–25 h 189 136 (71.96%) 53 (28.04%)
25–38 h 311 182 (58.52%) 129 (41.48%)
>38 h 86 42 (48.84%) 44 (51.16%)
Near-work distance P 0.017**
=
>33 cm 283 188 (66.43%) 95 (33.57%)
<33 cm 303 172 (56.77%) 131 (43.23%)
Times of eye exercise per week P 0.280
=
1–5 times 285 183 (64.21%) 102 (35.79%)
5–10 times 246 140 (56.91%) 106 (43.09%)
10–20 times 52 35 (67.31%) 17 (32.69%)
>20 times 3 2 (66.67%) 1 (33.33%)
Times of visual fatigue per week P 0.021*
=
0 time 338 221 (65.38%) 117 (34.62%)
1–5 times 231 134 (58.01%) 97 (41.99%)
5–10 times 12 4 (33.33%) 8 (66.67%)
> 10 times 5 1 (20.00%) 4 (80.00%)
Reading posture P 0.022*
=
Sitting 365 235 (64.38%) 130 (35.62%)
Prone 175 93 (53.14%) 82 (46.86%)
Supine 46 32 (69.57%) 14 (30.43%)
Distance between fingertip and nib P 0.082
=
<1.5 cm 218 124 (56.88%) 94 (43.12%)
>1.5 cm 368 236 (64.13%) 132 (35.87%)
Head angle P 0.233
=
Vertical 0° 44 26 (59.09%) 18 (40.91%)
Left 0°–45° 217 128 (58.99%) 89 (41.01%)
Left 45°–90° 250 165 (66.00%) 85 (34.00%)
Right 0°–45° 57 30 (52.63%) 27 (47.37%)
Right 45°–90° 18 9 (50%) 9 (50%)
Light environment in classroom P < 0.001**
Closed curtains 92 39 (42.39%) 53 (57.61%)
--- 第 6 頁 ---
Liu et al. BMC Ophthalmology (2023) 23:1 Page 6 of 10
Table 1 (continued)
Characteristics All participants Subgroup participants P value
(586)
Non-myopia (360) Myopia (226)
Open curtains 516 335 (64.92%) 181 (35.08%)
Outdoor time per week P 0.026*
=
0–7 h 268 150 (55.97%) 118 (44.03%)
7–14 h 257 166 (64.59%) 91 (35.41%)
>14 h 61 44 (72.13%) 17 (27.87%)
Parents with myopia P 0.002*
=
0 133 96 (72.18%) 37 (27.82%)
1 253 158 (62.45%) 95 (37.55%)
2 200 106 (53.00%) 94 (47.00%)
Parents with high myopia P 0.532
=
0 422 257 (60.90%) 165 (39.10%)
1 130 79 (60.77%) 51 (39.23%)
2 34 24 (70.59%) 10 (29.41%)
Vegetable intake per day P 0.852
=
< 75 g 179 113 (63.13%) 66 (36.87%)
75–150 g 312 189 (60.58%) 123 (39.42%)
> 150 g 95 58 (61.05%) 37 (38.95%)
Fruit intake per day P 0.545
=
<75 g 295 177 (60.00%) 118 (40.00%)
75–150 g 244 156 (63.93%) 88 (36.07%)
>150 g 47 27 (57.45%) 20 (42.55%)
Percentage of grains in staple foods P 0.052
=
<25% 362 213 (58.84%) 149 (41.16%)
25–50% 179 112 (62.57%) 67 (37.43%)
>50% 45 35 (77.78%) 10 (22.22%)
School type P 0.107
=
Public schools 560 348 (62.14%) 212 (37.86%)
Private schools 26 12 (46.15%) 14 (53.85%)
*, P < 0.05 is significant; **, P < 0.001 is highly significant
Fig. 1 Forest plot showing the risk/protective factors for myopia in multivariate logistic analysis
--- 第 7 頁 ---
L iu et al. BMC Ophthalmology (2023) 23:1 Page 7 of 10
Table 2 Effect of whole-grain consumption on the odds of Table 3 Effect of whole-grain intake on myopia stratified by sex
myopia in Models 1–5 and age (Adjusted OR and 95% confidence intervals)
Whole grains: 25–50% Whole grains: >50% Proportion of whole-grain intake P-trend
Crude model
< 25% 25–50% > 50%
OR 1.033 0.376
Sex
95% CI 0.672–1.589 0.165–0.856
Female 1 1.663 (0.767– 0.214 (0.049– 0.390
P-value 0.881 0.020 3.604) 0.938) *
Model 1 Male 1 0.739 (0.347– 0.209 (0.045– 0.169
OR 1.033 0.376 1.573) 0.979) *
95% CI 0.672–1.589 0.165–0.856 Age
P-value 0.881 0.020 6–8 years 1 0.903 (0.429– 0.412 (0.113– 0.239
1.898) 1.494)
Model 2
9–12 years 1 1.413 (0.663– 0.196 (0.044– 0.115
OR 1.160 0.381
3.010) 0.872) *
95% CI 0.742–1.814 0.161–0.900
The reference category was whole grain (WG) intake < 25%
P-value 0.516 0.028
Multivariable logistic regression was used to estimate the association between
Model 3 WG intake and incidence of myopia. When stratified by sex and age, all elements
OR 1.221 0.398 were adjusted in the models, except for themselves
95% CI 0.759–1.966 0.162–0.983 OR Odds ratio
P-value 0.411 0.046 * P <0.05
Model 4
OR 1.252 0.393
95% CI 0.774–2.025 0.158–0.974 variations in chromatic light composition, higher light
P-value 0.360 0.044 intensities, and increased release of dopamine from the
Model 5 retina, which can slow axial elongation [34–38].
OR 1.217 0.370 Gardiner [39] has suggested that accelerated growth
95% CI 0.745–1.990 0.147–0.935 patterns are associated with refractive errors in myo-
P-value 0.433 0.036 pia, and that diet may be a potential environmental ele-
ment common to both generalised accelerated growth
The reference category was WG intake < 25%
and the onset of myopia progression. The results indi-
In the crude model: no adjustment, whole grains 25% were taken as reference.
≤
In Model 1, sex, age, and school type were adjusted. In Model 2, parental myopia cated that WG intake was an independent protective
was also included. In Model 3, near-work activity, reading and writing habits,
factor against myopia, and only those with > 50% WGs
screen time, eye exercise, and visual fatigue times per week were subsequently
entered into the model. In Model 4, outdoor time and light environment in the in their total grain-based food received significant ben-
classroom were further entered into the model. In Model 5, the intake of fruits efits after adjusting for vegetable intake, fruit intake, and
and vegetables were also entered into the model
other covariates. Therefore, a beneficial link between WG
CI Confidence interval, OR Odds ratio
intake and myopia can be attributed to specific factors
associated with WGs.
Myopia is caused by environmental or genetic factors
various factors, rather than a single isolated factor, may
resulting in abnormal visual information acting on the
determine the refractive state. In addition, we found
retina, which is formed by retinal pigment epithelial–
that sex was associated with myopia, with reduced
choroidal signal transduction. This ultimately acts on the
probability for boys (OR 0.544, P 0.006). This is
= = sclera and initiates scleral remodelling. Dietary changes,
likely because females spend more time studying, read-
including increased consumption of high-glycaemic car-
ing, and practising near-work and less time on outdoor
bohydrates, may also affect the structure of the growing
activities at all ages [25, 32]. Among the associated fac-
eyes [40, 41] and lead to unregulated cell proliferation in
tors for myopia in the multivariable logistic regression
scleral tissue [42]. WG foods are a healthier option than
analysis, we were particularly surprised by the mark-
refined grains and include some parts of the grain that are
edly lower prevalence of myopia in the participants
removed during processing. WGs are nutritionally supe-
where classroom curtains were often open. This would
rior to refined grains because they are a major contribu-
be consistent with the light effects reported by Cohen
tor of fibre; vitamins; minerals; zinc; and phytoestrogens,
and Iribarren [33]. The link between light exposure and
such as lignins [43]. Importantly, WGs contain higher
the prevalence of myopia has not been fully elucidated;
amounts of dietary fibre than refined grains, and there is
however, the proposed reasons include factors such as
substantial collinearity between estimates of WG intake
--- 第 8 頁 ---
Liu et al. BMC Ophthalmology (2023) 23:1 Page 8 of 10
and cereal fibre intake [44]. Increased WG intake may non-significant in children aged 6–8 years, while WG
release various dietary fibres that can slow the absorption intake > 50% remained protective against myopia in chil-
and digestion of carbohydrates, reducing insulin demand dren aged 9–12 years. This is likely due to the increased
[45]. An evolutionary analyses of the cause of myopia in intensive near-work and educational pressures and less
adolescents by Cordain et al. [9] suggested that hyper- outdoor activities in older children. This also suggests
insulinemia diets promote myopic axial elongation by that the dietary hypothesis cannot be tested indepen-
increasing insulin-like growth factor-1 circulation, reduc- dently, since the type and quantity of diet are associated
ing growth hormone circulation, and contributing to with physical activities, which may be negatively cor-
scleral growth through vitamin A and retinoid receptor related with time spent in near-work and outdoors [56,
signalling. Evidence from animal models also supports 57]. In this study, a multivariable analysis of intake of
the possible mechanism through which high insulin lev- WGs in relation to myopia showed that WG intake > 50%
els can trigger myopia. Experiments performed in chick- remained protective against myopia after multivariable
ens revealed that intravitreal insulin injection inhibited adjustment for time spent in near-work and outdoors.
choroid thickening, elongated the anterior chamber, Finally, we also hypothesise that diets in cities or higher
and thickened the lens, accelerating lens-induced axial socioeconomic status families are more likely to be defi-
myopia and inhibiting lens-induced hyperopia [46, 47]. cient in WG. As children from these backgrounds are
Moreover, a higher total fibre intake was linked to a lower likely to be myopic due to factors other than diet, this
intake of total calories, including saturated fat, which is suggests a non-causal association of WG consumption
a known contributing factor to insulin resistance and with myopia, which could make the idea of dietary sup-
an insulin antagonist [48, 49]. Laurence et al. [11] have plementation implausible. Further studies need to con-
reported that a higher saturated fat and cholesterol sider the socio-demographic risk factors to assess this
intake was associated with a longer axial length. This was possibility and investigate the underlying mechanisms by
similarly reported by Gardiner, who compared the diet of which WGs can affect myopia.
33 active myopic and 251 stable myopic individuals and As mentioned, dietary intake is complex and highly
showed increased consumption of lipids and carbohy- variable. Factors such as environmental exposure and
drates in the active group, suggesting the involvement of dietary assessment in this study may not be robust,
diet in the pathophysiology of myopia [50]. These find- as WGs are diverse, and we only assessed late-life diet.
ings support the hyperinsulinemia theory proposed by Additionally, because the dietary data were self-reported
Cordain et al. [9]. and collected retrospectively, subjecting it to recall
A plausible alternative hypothesis is that dietary sup- errors, the information on WGs may not be accurate.
plements with WG could prevent the development and Therefore, these findings should be replicated in other
progression of myopia as they contain calcium, iron, populations and compared with other dietary assessment
magnesium, manganese, copper, and zinc. These dietary methods.
supplements play an essential role in antioxidative pro- Details on diet and an extensive list of covariates were
cesses and the biochemical remodelling of the sclera [51– collected using a questionnaire. Although this has obvi-
54], which is important in facilitating the increase in axial ous limitations, the results are still credible to some
length that results in myopia [55]. Huibi et al. have also extent. First, our questionnaire was designed considering
revealed that zinc supplements in animal diets lead to questionnaires developed and used successfully in other
the upregulation of copper–zinc superoxide dismutase, studies [36, 58, 59] and experts approved the final ques-
thereby inhibiting axial eyeball elongation [51]. tionnaire. Second, the questionnaire was independently
Moreover, our study found that WGs remained the used by members of our research group with several
main determinants when analyses were stratified by sex. years of experience in preventing and controlling myopia.
However, Berticat et al. [10] discovered that refined car- To explore the relationship between WG and myopia,
bohydrate consumption is associated with myopia in chil- factors related to myopia were included as covariates to
dren aged 5–19 years in a French paediatric population, adjust for potential confounding effects. Last, if the same
with increased odds for girls and reduced odds for boys, answer items were more than 70% for all the question-
possibly since chronic hyperglycemia is not commonly naire items, the questionnaire was considered invalid,
observed among boys due to their higher physical activ- thus ensuring the credibility of our results.
ity at all ages [10]. This study observed that intake > 50%
Conclusion
of WGs was identified as a protective factor against myo-
pia for boys and girls. However, a different relationship A clear inverse association was observed between the
between WGs and myopia in the two groups (6–8years prevalence of myopia and WG intake. A higher propor-
vs. 9–12 years) was observed, wherein WG intake was tion of WG intake had a protective effect against myopia
--- 第 9 頁 ---
L iu et al. BMC Ophthalmology (2023) 23:1 Page 9 of 10
development. Interestingly, modifying the form of grains myopia and temporal Trends from 2000 through 2050. Ophthalmology.
2016;123(5):1036–42.
consumed (whole vs. refined) could be a potential public
2. Ohno-Matsui K, Lai T, Lai C, Cheung C. Updates of pathologic myopia.
health measure against myopia. As this study was explor- Prog Retin Eye Res. 2016;52:156–87.
atory, the data supporting this hypothesis are limited 3. Saw SM, Chua WH, Hong CY, Wu HM, Tan D. Nearwork in early-onset
myopia. Invest Ophthalmol Vis. 2002;43(2):332–9.
and it is not easy to provide strong evidence to establish
4. Saw SM, Nieto FJ, Katz J, Schein OD, Levy B, Chew SJ. Familial cluster-
accurate links between benefits of whole grain consump- ing and myopia progression in Singapore school children. Ophthalmic
tion and myopia. Therefore, further studies are warranted Epidemiol. 2001;8(4):227–36.
5. Saw S. A synopsis of the prevalence rates and environmental risk factors
to validate our findings and investigate the underlying
for myopia. Clin experimental optometry. 2003;86(5):289–94.
mechanisms by which WGs can affect myopia. 6. Fernández-Montero A, Olmo-Jimenez JM, Olmo N, Bes-Rastrollo M,
Moreno-Galarraga L, Moreno-Montañés J, Martínez-González MA. The
impact of computer use in myopia progression: a cohort study in Spain.
Abbreviations Prev Med. 2015;71:67–71.
WGs: Whole grains; OR: Odds ratio. 7. Chen S, Guo Y, Han X, Yu X, Chen Q, Wang D, et al. Axial growth driven by
physical development and Myopia among children: a two year cohort
Acknowledgements study. J Clin Med. 2022;11(13). https:// www. mdpi. com/ 2077- 0383/ 11/ 13/
Not applicable. 3642.
8. Fenton A, Kisban E. Food in change: eating habits from the middle ages
Authors’ contributions to the present day. 1986. https:// agris. fao. org/ agris- search/ search. do?
RW and BD conceived and supervised the experiment. NJ and ZL determined recor dID XF201 60023 00.
=
the methods. QW and DW performed the study. ZL and QW analysed the data. 9. Cordain L, Eaton S, Brand Miller J, Lindeberg S, Jensen C. An evolutionary
ZL interpreted the data and wrote the manuscript. FG, QZ, and BW revised the analysis of the aetiology and pathogenesis of juvenile-onset myopia.
manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript. Acta Ophthalmol Scand. 2002;80(2):125–35.
10. Berticat C, Mamouni S, Ciais A, Villain M, Raymond M, Daien V. Probability
Funding of myopia in children with high refined carbohydrates consumption in
The authors declare that this study received funding from the Science & France. BMC Ophthalmol. 2020;20(1):337.
Technology Development Fund of Tianjin Education Commission for Higher 11. Lim LS, Gazzard G, Low YL, Choo R, Tan DT, Tong L, Yin Wong T, Saw SM.
Education of China (No. 2018KJ056) and the National Natural Science Founda- Dietary factors, myopia, and axial dimensions in children. Ophthalmology.
tion of China (No. 82070929). The funder was not involved in the study design; 2010;117(5):993–7.e994.
the collection, analysis, or interpretation of data; the writing of this article; or 12. Wang P, Liu X, Ye Z, Gong B, Yang Y, Zhang D, Wu X, Zheng H, Li Y, Yang Z,
the decision to submit it for publication. et al. Association of IGF1 and IGF1R gene polymorphisms with high myo-
pia in a Han Chinese population. Ophthalmic Genet. 2017;38(2):122–6.
Availability of data and materials 13. Sheng C, Zhu X, Wallman J. In vitro effects of insulin and RPE on
The datasets used and analysed during the current study are available from choroidal and scleral components of eye growth in chicks. Exp Eye Res.
the corresponding author (rwei@tmu.edu.cn) upon reasonable request. 2013;116:439–48.
14. Liu X, Wang P, Qu C, Zheng H, Gong B, Ma S, Lin H, Cheng J, Yang Z, Lu
F, et al. Genetic association study between INSULIN pathway related
Declarations genes and high myopia in a Han Chinese population. Mol Biol Rep.
2015;42(1):303–10.
Ethics approval and consent to participate 15. Tang RH, Tan J, Deng ZH, Zhao SZ, Miao YB, Zhang WJ. Insulin-like growth
This study was approved by the Human Research Ethics Committee of Tianjin factor-2 antisense oligonucleotides inhibits myopia by expression
Medical University Eye Hospital (2019KY-12) and was conducted following blocking of retinal insulin-like growth factor-2 in guinea pig. Clin Exp
the Declaration of Helsinki. The children were aged 6–12 years, and parents Ophthalmol. 2012;40(5):503–11.
or legal guardians of all participants provided written informed consent on 16. Meyer K, Kushi L, Jacobs D, Slavin J, Sellers T, Folsom A. Carbohydrates,
behalf of the participants. dietary fiber, and incident type 2 diabetes in older women. Am J Clin
Nutr. 2000;71(4):921–30.
Consent for publication 17. Liu S, Manson J, Stampfer M, Hu F, Giovannucci E, Colditz G, Hennekens
Not applicable. C, Willett W. A prospective study of whole-grain intake and risk of type 2
diabetes mellitus in US women. Am J Public Health. 2000;90(9):1409–15.
Competing interests 18. Kushi LH, Folsom AR, Prineas RJ, Mink PJ, Wu Y, Bostick RM. Dietary antioxi-
The authors declare that they have no competing interests. dant vitamins and death from coronary heart disease in postmenopausal
women. N Engl J Med. 1996;334(18):1156–62.
Author details 19. Potter JD. Food and phytochemicals, magic bullets and measurement
1 Tianjin Key Laboratory of Retinal Functions and Diseases, Tianjin Branch error: a commentary. Am J Epidemiol. 1996;144(11):1026–7.
of National Clinical Research Center for Ocular Disease, Eye Institute, School 20. Jacobs D, Meyer K, Kushi L, Folsom A. Whole-grain intake may reduce the
of Optometry, Tianjin Medical University Eye Hospital, Tianjin, China. 2 State Key risk of ischemic heart disease death in postmenopausal women: the Iowa
Laboratory of Experimental Hematology, National Clinical Research Center Women’s Health Study. Am J Clin Nutr. 1998;68(2):248–57.
for Blood Diseases, Institute of Hematology & Blood Diseases Hospital, Chinese 21. Snetselaar L, de Jesus J, DeSilva D, Stoody E. Dietary guidelines for Ameri-
Academy of Medical Sciences & Peking Union Medical College, Tianjin, China. cans, 2020–2025: understanding the scientific process, Guidelines, and
key recommendations. Nutr Today. 2021;56(6):287–95.
Received: 8 July 2022 Accepted: 30 December 2022 22. Saw S, Nieto F, Katz J, Schein O, Levy B, Chew S. Factors related to
the progression of myopia in singaporean children. Optom Vis Sci.
2000;77(10):549–54.
23. Wu PC, Huang HM, Yu HJ, Fang PC, Chen CT. Epidemiology of myopia.
Asia Pac J Ophthalmol (Phila). 2016;5(6):386–93.
References 24. Saw S, Hong C, Chia K, Stone R, Tan D. Nearwork and myopia in young
1. Holden B, Fricke T, Wilson D, Jong M, Naidoo K, Sankaridurg P, Wong children. Lancet (London England). 2001;357(9253):390.
T, Naduvilath T, Resnikoff S. Global prevalence of myopia and high
--- 第 10 頁 ---
Liu et al. BMC Ophthalmology (2023) 23:1 Page 10 of 10
25. Dirani M, Tong L, Gazzard G, Zhang X, Chia A, Young TL, Rose KA, Mitchell another clinical manifestation of insulin resistance? Med Hypotheses.
P, Saw SM. Outdoor activity and myopia in Singapore teenage children. Br 2016;90:32–40.
J Ophthalmol. 2009;93(8):997–1000. 48. Kennedy A, Martinez K, Chuang CC, LaPoint K, McIntosh M. Saturated
26. Pärssinen O, Kauppinen M. What is the influence of parents’ myopia on fatty acid-mediated inflammation and insulin resistance in adipose tissue:
their children’s myopic progression? A 22-year follow-up study. Acta mechanisms of action and implications. J Nutr. 2009;139(1):1–4.
Ophthalmol. 2016;94(6):579–85. 49. Erkkilä A, Herrington D, Mozaffarian D, Lichtenstein A. Cereal fiber and
27. Zhang X, Qu X, Zhou X. Association between parental myopia and the whole-grain intake are associated with reduced progression of coronary-
risk of myopia in a child. Exp Ther Med. 2015;9(6):2420–8. artery atherosclerosis in postmenopausal women with coronary artery
28. Wallman J. Parental history and myopia: taking the long view. JAMA. disease. Am Heart J. 2005;150(1):94–101.
1994;272(16):1255–6. 50. Gardiner PA. The diet of growing myopes. Trans Ophthalmol Soc U K.
29. Clark R, Pozarickij A, Hysi P, Ohno-Matsui K, Williams C, Guggenheim J. 1956;76:171–80.
Education interacts with genetic variants near GJD2, RBFOX1, LAMA2, 51. Huibi X, Kaixun H, Qiuhua G, Yushan Z, Xiuxian H. Prevention of axial
KCNQ5 and LRRC4C to confer susceptibility to myopia. PLoS Genet. elongation in myopia by the trace element zinc. Biol Trace Elem Res.
2022;18(11):e1010478. 2001;79(1):39–47.
30. Tedja M, Haarman A, Meester-Smoor M, Kaprio J, Mackey D, Guggenheim 52. Sukalski KA, LaBerge TP, Johnson WT. In vivo oxidative modification of
J, Hammond C, Verhoeven V, Klaver C. IMI - Myopia Genetics Report. erythrocyte membrane proteins in copper deficiency. Free Radic Biol
Investig Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2019;60(3):M89–105. Med. 1997;22(5):835–42.
31. Hysi P, Choquet H, Khawaja A, Wojciechowski R, Tedja M, Yin J, Simcoe M, 53. Rucker RB, Kosonen T, Clegg MS, Mitchell AE, Rucker BR, Uriu-Hare JY,
Patasova K, Mahroo O, Thai K, et al. Meta-analysis of 542,934 subjects of Keen CL. Copper, lysyl oxidase, and extracellular matrix protein cross-
european ancestry identifies new genes and mechanisms predisposing linking. Am J Clin Nutr. 1998;67(5 Suppl):996s–1002s.
to refractive error and myopia. Nat Genet. 2020;52(4):401–7. 54. Avetisov ES, Vinetskaia MI, Iomdina EN, Makhmudova FR, Boltaeva ZK,
32. Guo L, Yang J, Mai J, Du X, Guo Y, Li P, Yue Y, Tang D, Lu C, Zhang WH. Tarutta EP. [Copper metabolism in scleral tissue and possibilities of its
Prevalence and associated factors of myopia among primary and middle correction in myopia]. Vestn Oftalmol. 1991;107(5):31–4.
school-aged students: a school-based study in Guangzhou. Eye (Lond). 55. McBrien N, Jobling A, Gentle A. Biomechanics of the sclera in myopia:
2016;30(6):796–804. extracellular and cellular factors. Optom Vis Sci. 2009;86(1):E23-30.
33. Cohen Y, Iribarren R, Ben-Eli H, Massarwa A, Shama-Bakri N, Chassid O. 56. Sisson SB, Broyles ST, Baker BL, Katzmarzyk PT. Screen time, physical
Light intensity in Nursery Schools: a possible factor in Refractive Develop- activity, and overweight in U.S. youth: national survey of children’s health
ment. Asia Pac J Ophthalmol (Phila). 2022;11(1):66–71. 2003. J Adolesc Health. 2010;47(3):309–11.
34. Guggenheim J, Northstone K, McMahon G, Ness A, Deere K, Mattocks C, 57. Sandercock GR, Ogunleye A, Voss C. Screen time and physical activ-
Pourcain B, Williams C. Time outdoors and physical activity as predictors ity in youth: thief of time or lifestyle choice? J Phys Act Health.
of incident myopia in childhood: a prospective cohort study. Investig 2012;9(7):977–84.
Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2012;53(6):2856–65. 58. Qi L, Yao L, Wang X, Shi J, Liu Y, Wu T, Zou Z. Risk factors for Incident Myo-
35. Cao K, Wan Y, Yusufu M, Wang N. Significance of Outdoor Time for Myopia pia among Teenaged students of the experimental class of the Air Force
Prevention: a systematic review and Meta-analysis based on randomized in China. J Ophthalmol. 2019;2019:3096152.
controlled trials. Ophthalmic Res. 2020;63(2):97–105. 59. Low W, Dirani M, Gazzard G, Chan Y, Zhou H, Selvaraj P, Au Eong K, Young
36. Flitcroft D. The complex interactions of retinal, optical and environmental T, Mitchell P, Wong T, et al. Family history, near work, outdoor activity,
factors in myopia aetiology. Prog Retin Eye Res. 2012;31(6):622–60. and myopia in Singapore Chinese preschool children. Br J Ophthalmol.
37. Li X, Schaeffel F, Kohler K, Zrenner E. Dose-dependent effects of 2010;94(8):1012–6.
6-hydroxy dopamine on deprivation myopia, electroretinograms, and
dopaminergic amacrine cells in chickens. Vis Neurosci. 1992;9(5):483–92.
Publisher’s Note
38. Schaeffel F, Hagel G, Bartmann M, Kohler K, Zrenner E. 6-Hydroxy
dopamine does not affect lens-induced refractive errors but suppresses Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in pub-
deprivation myopia. Vis Res. 1994;34(2):143–9. lished maps and institutional affiliations.
39. Gardiner PA. Dietary treatment of myopia in children. Lancet.
1958;1(7031):1152–5.
40. Chiu CJ, Milton RC, Klein R, Gensler G, Taylor A. Dietary carbohydrate
and the progression of age-related macular degeneration: a prospec-
tive study from the Age-Related Eye Disease Study. Am J Clin Nutr.
2007;86(4):1210–8.
41. Chiu CJ, Hubbard LD, Armstrong J, Rogers G, Jacques PF, Chylack LT Jr,
Hankinson SE, Willett WC, Taylor A. Dietary glycemic index and carbo-
hydrate in relation to early age-related macular degeneration. Am J Clin
Nutr. 2006;83(4):880–6.
42. Liu B, Lee HY, Weinzimer SA, Powell DR, Clifford JL, Kurie JM, Cohen P.
Direct functional interactions between insulin-like growth factor-binding
Protein-3 and Retinoid X Receptor-α regulate Transcriptional Signaling
and apoptosis. J Biol Chem. 2000;275(43):33607–13.
43. Slavin J, Jacobs D, Marquart L. Whole-grain consumption and chronic RReeaaddyy ttoo ssuubbmmiitt yyoouurr rreesseeaarrcchh ?? CChhoooossee BBMMCC aanndd bbeenneeffiitt ffrroomm::
disease: protective mechanisms. Nutr Cancer. 1997;27(1):14–21.
• fast, convenient online submission
44. Reicks M, Jonnalagadda S, Albertson A, Joshi N. Total dietary fiber intakes
in the US population are related to whole grain consumption: results • thorough peer review by experienced rese archers in your field
from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 2009 to 2010. • rapid publication on acceptance
Nutr Res (New York NY). 2014;34(3):226–34.
• support for research data, including large and complex data types
45. Slavin JL, Martini MC, Jacobs DR Jr, Marquart L. Plausible mechanisms
for the protectiveness of whole grains. Am J Clin Nutr. 1999;70(3 • gold Open Access which fosters wider collaboration and increased citations
Suppl):459s–463s. • maximum visibility for your research: over 100M website views per year
46. Zhu X, Wallman J. Opposite effects of glucagon and insulin on com-
pensation for spectacle lenses in chicks. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. At BMC, research is always in progress.
2009;50(1):24–36.
47. Galvis V, López-Jaramillo P, Tello A, Castellanos-Castellanos YA, Cama- Learn more biomedcentral.com/submissions
cho PA, Cohen DD, Gómez-Arbeláez D, Merayo-Lloves J. Is myopia
